<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-ietf-idr-bgp-ct-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP Classful Transport Planes">BGP Classful Transport
    Planes</title>

    <author fullname="Kaliraj Vairavakkalai" initials="K." role="editor"
            surname="Vairavakkalai">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kaliraj@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Natrajan Venkataraman" initials="N." role="editor"
            surname="Venkataraman">
      <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>natv@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="31" month="12" year="2022"/>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies a mechanism, referred to as "Intent Driven
      Service Mapping" to express association of overlay routes with underlay
      routes satisfying a certain SLA using BGP. The document describes a
      framework for classifying underlay routes into transport classes and
      mapping service routes to specific transport class.</t>

      <t>The "Transport class" construct maps to a desired SLA and can be used
      to realize the "Topology Slice" in 5G Network slicing architecture.</t>

      <t>This document specifies BGP protocol procedures that enable
      dissemination of such service mapping information that may span multiple
      cooperating administrative domains. These domains may be administetered
      by the same provider or by closely co-ordinating provider networks.</t>

      <t>A new BGP transport layer address family (SAFI 76) is defined for
      this purpose that uses RFC-4364 technology and follows RFC-8277 NLRI
      encoding. This new address family is called "BGP Classful Transport",
      aka BGP CT.</t>

      <t>BGP CT makes it possible to advertise multiple tunnels to the same
      destination address, thus avoiding need of multiple loopbacks on the
      egress node.</t>

      <t>It carries transport prefixes across tunnel domain boundaries (e.g.
      in Inter-AS Option-C networks), which is parallel to BGP LU (SAFI 4) .
      It disseminates "Transport class" information for the transport prefixes
      across the participating domains, which is not possible with BGP LU.
      This makes the end-to-end network a "Transport Class" aware tunneled
      network.</t>

      <t>Just like BGP LU (SAFI 4), BGP CT family (SAFI 76) is used in
      inter-AS option-C networks. The Service Mapping procedures described in
      this document apply in the same manner to Intra-AS service end points as
      well as Inter-AS option-A, option-B, option-C variations. Examples of
      these variations are given in Appendix A.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The mechanisms defined in this document enable brownfiled networks
      deployed using existing technologies like RSVP-TE and greenfield
      networks that use technologies like SPRING achieve 'Intent Driven
      Service Mapping'.</t>

      <t>To facilitate this, the tunnels in a network can be grouped by the
      purpose they serve into a "Transport Class". These tunnels could be
      created using any signaling protocol including but not limited to LDP,
      RSVP-TE, BGP LU or SPRING. The tunnels could also use native IP or IPv6
      as long as they can carry MPLS payload. Tunnels may exist between
      different pair of end points. Multiple tunnels may exist between the
      same pair of end points.</t>

      <t>Thus, a Transport Class consists of tunnels created by various
      protocols that satisfy the properties of the class. For example, a
      "Gold" transport class may consist of tunnels that traverse the shortest
      path with fast re-route protection. A "Silver" transport class may hold
      tunnels that traverse shortest paths without protection. A "To NbrAS
      Foo" transport class may hold tunnels that exit to neighboring AS Foo
      and so on.</t>

      <t>The extensions specified in this document can be used to create a BGP
      transport tunnel that potentially spans domains while preserving its
      Transport Class. Examples of domain are Autonomous System (AS) or IGP
      area. Within each domain, there is a second level underlay tunnel used
      by BGP to cross the domain. The second level underlay tunnels could be
      hetrogeneous; each domain may use a different type of tunnel (e.g. MPLS,
      IP, GRE or SRv6) or use a differnet signaling protocol. A domain
      boundary is demarcated by a rewrite of BGP nexthop to 'self' while
      readvertising tunnel routes in BGP CT. Examples of domain boundary are
      inter-AS links and inter-region ABRs. The path uses MPLS label-switching
      when crossing domain boundaries and uses the native intra-AS tunnel of
      the desired transport class when traversing within a domain.</t>

      <t>Overlay routes carry sufficient indication of the desired Transport
      Classes in the form of a BGP community called the "Mapping community".
      The "route resolution" procedure on the ingress node selects an
      appropriate tunnel whose destination matches (LPM) the nexthop of the
      overlay route belonging to the corresponding Transport Class. If the
      overlay route is carried in BGP, the protocol nexthop (or PNH) is
      carried as an attribute of the route.</t>

      <t>The PNH of the overlay route is also referred to as "Service
      Endpoint" (SEP). The SEP may exist in the same domain as the service
      ingress node or lie in a different domain, which is adjacent or
      non-adjacent. In the former case, reachability to the SEP is provided by
      an intra-domain tunneling protocol and in the latter case, reachability
      to the SEP is via BGP transport families (e.g. SAFI 4 or 76).</t>

      <t>In this architecture, the intra-domain transport protocols (e.g.
      RSVP-TE, SRTE) are also "Transport Class aware". They publish ingress
      routes in the Transport Route Database associated with the Transport
      Class at the tunnel ingress node. These routes are used to resolve BGP
      routes inluding BGP CT which may be further readvertised to adjacent
      domains to extend this tunnel. How exactly the transport protocols are
      made transport class aware is outside the scope of this document.</t>

      <t>This document describes mechanisms to: <list>
          <t>Model a "Transport Class" as a "Transport Route Database" on a
          router and to collect tunnel ingress routes of a certain class.</t>

          <t>Enable service routes to resolve over an intended Transport Class
          by virtue of carrying the appropriate "Mapping Community", which
          results in using the corresponding Transport Route Database for
          finding nexthop reachability.</t>

          <t>Publish tunnel ingress routes in a Transport Route Database via
          BGP without any path hiding using BGP VPN and Add-path procedures,
          such that overlay routes in the receiving domains can also resolve
          over tunnels of the associated Transport Class.</t>

          <t>Provide a way for cooperating domains to reconcile any
          differences in extended community namespaces and interoperate
          between different transport signaling protocols in each domain.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In this document we focus mainly on MPLS as the intra-domain
      transport tunnel forwarding technology, but the mechanisms described
      here would work in similar manner for non-MPLS (e.g. IP, GRE, UDP or
      SRv6) transport tunnel forwarding technologies too.</t>

      <t>This document assumes MPLS forwarding as the defacto standard when
      crossing domain boundaries. However mechanisms specified in this
      document can also support different forwarding technologies (e.g. SRv6).
      Section 17 (SRv6 support) in this document describes the application of
      BGP CT over SRv6 data plane.</t>

      <t>The document <xref target="Intent-Routing">Intent-aware Routing using
      Color </xref> describes various use cases and applications of procedures
      described in this document.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>LSP: Label Switched Path.</t>

      <t>TE : Traffic Engineering.</t>

      <t>SN : Service Node. A router that sends or receives BGP Service routes
      (e.g. SAFIs 1, 128) with self as nexthop.</t>

      <t>BN : Border Node. A router that sends or receives BGP Transport
      routes (e.g. SAFI 4, 76) with self as nexthop.</t>

      <t>TN : Transport Node, P-router.</t>

      <t>BGP-VPN : VPNs built using RFC4364 mechanisms.</t>

      <t>RT : Route-Target extended community.</t>

      <t>RD : Route-Distinguisher.</t>

      <t>VRF: Virtual Router Forwarding Table.</t>

      <t>CsC: Carrier serving Carrier VPN.</t>

      <t>PNH : Protocol-Nexthop address carried in a BGP Update message.</t>

      <t>EP : End point, a loopback address in the network.</t>

      <t>SEP : Service End point, the PNH of a Service route.</t>

      <t>LPM : Longest Prefix Match.</t>

      <t>SLA: Service Level Agreement.</t>

      <t>EPE: Egress Peer Engineering.</t>

      <t>Service Family : BGP address family used for advertising routes for
      "data traffic" as opposed to tunnels (e.g. SAFI 1 or 128).</t>

      <t>Transport Family : BGP address family used for advertising tunnels,
      which are in turn used by service routes for resolution (e.g. SAFI 4 or
      76).</t>

      <t>Transport Tunnel : A tunnel over which a service may place traffic
      (e.g. GRE, UDP, LDP, RSVP-TE or SPRING).</t>

      <t>Tunnel Ingress Route: Route to Tunnel Destination/Endpoint installed
      at the headend (ingress) of the tunnel by the tunneling protocol.</t>

      <t>Tunnel Domain : A domain of the network containing SNs and BNs under
      a single administrative control that has tunnels between them. An
      end-to-end tunnel spanning several adjacent tunnel domains can be
      created by "stitching" them together using labels.</t>

      <t>Transport Class : A group of transport tunnels offering the same
      SLA.</t>

      <t>Transport Class RT : A Route-Target extended community used to
      identify a specific Transport Class.</t>

      <t>Transport Route Database : At the SN and BN, a Transport Class has an
      associated Transport Route Database that collects its tunnel ingress
      routes.</t>

      <t>Transport Plane : An end to end plane comprising of transport tunnels
      belonging to same Transport Class. Tunnels of same Transport Class are
      stitched together by BGP CT route readvertisements with nexthop self to
      enable Label-Swap forwarding across domain boundaries.</t>

      <t>Mapping Community : BGP Community/Extended-community on a service
      route that maps it to resolve over a Transport Class.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transport Class">
      <t>A Transport Class is defined as a set of transport tunnels that share
      the same SLA. It is encoded as the Transport Class RT, which is a new
      Route-Target extended community.</t>

      <t>A Transport Class is configured at SN and BN with RD and Route Target
      attributes. Creation of a Transport Class instantiates its corresponding
      Transport Route Database.</t>

      <t>The operator may configure an SN/BN to classify a tunnel into an
      appropriate Transport Class, which causes the tunnel's ingress route to
      be installed in the corresponding Transport Route Database. These routes
      are used to resolve BGP routes inluding BGP CT which may be further
      readvertised to adjacent domains to extend this tunnel.</t>

      <t>Alternatively, a router receiving the transport routes in BGP with
      appropriate signaling information can associate those ingress routes to
      the appropriate Transport Class. E.g. for Classful Transport family
      (SAFI 76) routes, the Transport Class RT indicates the Transport Class.
      For BGP LU family(SAFI 4) routes, import processing based on Communities
      or inter-AS source-peer may be used to place the route in the desired
      Transport Class.</t>

      <t>When the ingress route is received via <xref
      target="SRTE">SRTE</xref> with "Color:Endpoint" as the NLRI that encodes
      the Transport Class as an integer 'Color', the 'Color' is mapped to a
      Transport Class during import processing. SRTE ingress route for
      'Endpoint' is installed in the corresponding Transport Route Database.
      The SRTE tunnel will be extended by a BGP CT advertisement with NLRI
      'RD:Endpoint', Transport Class RT and a new label. The MPLS swap route
      thus installed for the new label will pop the label and deliver
      decapsulated traffic into the path determined by SRTE route.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8664">RFC8664</xref> extends PCEP to carry SRTE
      Color. This color association learnt from PCEP is also mapped to a
      Transport Class thus associating the PCEP signaled SRTE LSP with the
      desired Transport Class.</t>

      <t>Similarly, <xref target="PCEP-RSVP-COLOR">PCEP-RSVP-COLOR</xref>
      extends PCEP to carry RSVP Color. This color association learnt from
      PCEP is also mapped to a Transport Class thus associating the PCEP
      signaled RSVP-TE LSP with the desired Transport Class.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="&quot;Transport Class&quot; Route Target Extended Community">
      <t>This document defines a new type of Route Target, called "Transport
      Class" Route Target Extended Community.</t>

      <t>"Transport Class" Route Target extended community is a transitive
      extended community <xref target="RFC4360">EXT-COMM</xref> of
      extended-type, with a new Format (Type high = 0xa) and SubType as 0x2
      (Route Target).</t>

      <t>This new Route Target Format has the following encoding:</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">



 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|   Type= 0xa   | SubType= 0x02 |            Reserved           |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                     Transport Class ID                        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

      Fig 1: "Transport Class" Route Target Extended Community

 Type: 1 octet

    Type field contains value 0xa.

 SubType: 1 octet

    Subtype field contain 0x2. This indicates 'Route Target'.

 Transport Class ID: 4 octets

    The least significant 32-bits of the value field contain the 
    "Transport Class" identifier, which is a 32-bit integer. 

 The remaining 2 octets after SubType field are Reserved. They MUST 
 be set to zero on transmission, SHOULD be ignored on reception and
 left unaltered.
 
</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The "Transport class" Route Target Extended community follows the
      mechanisms for VPN route import/export as specified in <xref
      target="RFC4364">BGP-VPN</xref> and follows the Constrained Route
      Distribution mechanisms as specified in <xref target="RFC4684">Route
      Target Constraints</xref></t>

      <t>A BGP speaker that implements RT Constraint <xref
      target="RFC4684">Route Target Constraints</xref> MUST apply the RT
      Constraint procedures to the "Transport class" Route Target Extended
      community as well.</t>

      <t>The Transport Class Route Target Extended community is carried on
      Classful Transport family routes and allows associating them with
      appropriate Transport Route Databases at receiving BGP speakers.</t>

      <t>Use of the Transport Class Route Target Extended community with a new
      Type code avoids conflicts with any VPN Route Target assignments already
      in use for service families.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transport Route Database">
      <t>A Transport Route Database is a logical collection of transport
      routes pertaining to the same Transport Class. Tunnel endpoint addresses
      in this database belong to the "Provider Namespace".</t>

      <t>Overlay routes that want to use a specific Transport Class confine
      the scope of nexthop resolution to the set of routes contained in the
      corresponding Transport Route Database.</t>

      <t>The Transport Route Database can be realized as a "Routing Table"
      referred in <eref
      target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4271#section-9.1.2.1">Section
      9.1.2.1 of RFC4271</eref> which is a control plane only database.
      However, an implementation may choose a different methodology to realize
      this logical construct in such a way that it supports the procedures
      defined in this document.</t>

      <t>SN or BN originate routes for 'Classful Transport' address family
      from the Transport Route Database. These routes have NLRI "RD:Endpoint",
      Transport Class RT and an MPLS label. 'Classful Transport' family routes
      received with Transport Class RT are imported into its corresponding
      Transport Route Database.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Nexthop Resolution Scheme">
      <t>An implementation may provide an option for the service route to
      resolve over less preferred Transport Classes, should the resolution
      over preferred or "primary" Transport Class fail.</t>

      <t>To accomplish this, the set of service routes may be associated with
      a user-configured "Resolution Scheme" that consists of the primary
      Transport Class and an optional ordered list of fallback Transport
      Classes.</t>

      <t>A community called as "Mapping Community" is configured for a
      "resolution scheme". A Mapping Community maps to exactly one Resolution
      Scheme. A Resolution Scheme comprises of one primary transport class and
      optionally, one or more fallback transport classes.</t>

      <t>A BGP route is associated with a resolution scheme during import
      processing. The first community on the route that matches a Mapping
      Community of a locally configured Resolution Scheme is considered the
      effective Mapping Community for the route. The Resolution Scheme thus
      found is used when resolving the route's PNH. If a route contains more
      than one Mapping Community, it indicates that the route considers these
      multiple Mapping Communities as equivalent. So, the first community that
      maps to a Resolution Scheme is chosen.</t>

      <t>A transport route received in BGP Classful Transport family SHOULD
      use a Resolution Scheme that contains the primary Transport Class
      without any fallback to best effort tunnels. The primary Transport Class
      is identified by the Transport Class RT carried on the route. Thus,
      Transport Class RT serves as the Mapping Community for BGP CT
      routes.</t>

      <t>A service route received in a BGP service family MAY map to a
      Resolution Scheme that contains the primary Transport Class identified
      by the Mapping Community on the route and a fallback to best effort
      Transport Class. The primary Transport Class is identified by the
      Mapping Community carried on the route. For e.g. the Extended Color
      community may serve as the Mapping Community for service routes.
      Color:0:&lt;n&gt; MAY map to a Resolution Scheme that has primary
      Transport Class &lt;n&gt; and a fallback to best-effort Transport
      Class.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="BGP Classful Transport Family NLRI">
      <t>The Classful Transport (CT) family will use the existing AFI of IPv4
      or IPv6 and a new SAFI 76 "Classful Transport" that will apply to both
      IPv4 and IPv6 AFIs. These AFI, SAFI pair of values MUST be negotiated in
      Multiprotocol Extensions capability described in <xref
      target="RFC4760"/> to be able to send and receive BGP CT routes.</t>

      <t>The "Classful Transport" SAFI NLRI itself is encoded as specified in
      <xref
      target="RFC8277">https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8277#section-2</xref>.</t>

      <t>When AFI/SAFI is 1/76, the Classful Transport NLRI Prefix consists of
      an 8-byte RD followed by an IPv4 prefix. When AFI/SAFI is 2/76, the
      Classful Transport NLRI Prefix consists of an 8-byte RD followed by an
      IPv6 prefix.</t>

      <t>Procedures described for SAFI 4 or SAFI 128 in <xref
      target="RFC8277">https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8277#section-2</xref>
      apply for SAFI 76 as well. BGP CT routes MAY carry multiple labels in
      the NLRI, by negotiating the Multiple Labels Capability as described in
      <xref
      target="RFC8277">https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc8277#section-2.1</xref></t>

      <t>For easy reference, the following figure illustrates a BGP Classful
      Transport family NLRI when single Label is advertised (Multiple Labels
      Capability is not negotiated):</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">

      0                   1                   2                   3
      0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |    Length     |                 Label                 |Rsrv |S|
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     ~                     Route Distinguisher (8 bytes)             |
     |                                                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
     |                     IPv4/IPv6 Prefix                          ~
     |                                                               |
     +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

         Fig 2: SAFI 76 "Classful Transport" NLRI

 Length: 1 octet

    The Length field consists of a single octet.  It specifies the
    length in bits of the remainder of the NLRI field.

    Note that the length will always be the sum of 20 (number of bits
    in Label field), plus 3 (number of bits in Rsrv field), plus 1
    (number of bits in S field), plus the length in bits of the
    Prefix (RD:IP prefix).

    In an MP_REACH_NLRI attribute whose SAFI is 76, the Prefix
    (RD + IP prefix) will be 96 bits or less if the AFI is 1 
    and will be 192 bits or less if the AFI is 2.
    
    As specified in [RFC4760], the actual length of the NLRI field
    will be the number of bits specified in the Length field, rounded
    up to the nearest integral number of octets.

 Label:

     The Label field is a 20-bit field containing an MPLS label value
     (see [RFC3032]).

 Rsrv:

     This 3-bit field SHOULD be set to zero on transmission and MUST be
     ignored on reception.

 S:
     When single label is advertised, this 1-bit field MUST be set to
     one on transmission and MUST be ignored on reception.
      

 Route Distinguihser: 
 
     8 byte RD as defined in [RFC4364 Sec 4.2].

 IPv4/IPv6 Prefix: 

    IPv4 prefix, if AFI/SAFI 1/76. 
    IPv6 prefix, if AFI/SAFI 2/76.

</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Attributes on a Classful Transport route include the Transport Class
      Route-Target extended community, which is used to associate the route
      with the correct Transport Route Databases on SNs and BNs in the
      network.</t>

      <t>SAFI 76 routes can be sent with either IPv4 or IPv6 nexthop. The type
      of nexthop is inferred from the length of the nexthop.</t>

      <t>When the length of Next Hop Address field is 24 (or 48) the nexthop
      address is of type VPN-IPv6 with 8-octet RD set to zero (potentially
      followed by the link-local VPN-IPv6 address of the next hop with an
      8-octet RD set to zero).</t>

      <t>When the length of the Next Hop Address field is 12 the nexthop
      address is of type VPN-IPv4 with 8-octet RD set to zero.</t>

      <section anchor="CTMultiEncap" title="Carrying multiple encapsulation information">
        <t>natv text</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Usage of Route Distinguisher and Label Allocation Modes">
      <t>RD aids in troubleshooting a BGP CT network by uniquely identifying
      the originator of a route across a multi domain network.</t>

      <t>Use of RD also allows the option for signaling forwarding diversity
      within the same Transport Class. The same Egress PE can advertise
      multiple BGP CT routes for an EP belonging to the same Transport
      Class.</t>

      <t>E.g. multiple RDx:EP1 prefixes can be advertised for an EP1 to
      different set of BGP peers in order to collect traffic statistics for
      them. In absense of RD, duplicated Transport Class/Color values will be
      needed in the transport network to achieve such use cases.</t>

      <t>In a BGP CT network, the number of routes at an Ingress PE is a
      function of unique EPs multiplied by BNs in the ingress domain that do
      nexthop self. BGP CT provides flexible RD and Label allocation modes to
      address operational requirements in a multi-domain network. </t>

      <t>The allocation of RD is done at the point of origin of the BGP CT
      route. This can either be an Egress SN or a BN. The default RD
      allocation mode is to use unique RD per originiating node for an EP.
      This mode allows for the ingress to uniquely identify each originated
      path. Alternatively, the same RD may be provisioned for multiple
      originators of the same EP. This mode can be used when the ingress does
      not require full visibility of all nodes originating an EP.</t>

      <t>A label is allocated for a BGP CT route when it is advertised with
      nexthop self by a SN or a BN. An implementation may use different label
      allocation modes with BGP-CT. The recommended label allocation mode is
      per-prefix as it provides better traffic convergence properties than
      per-nexthop label allocation mode. Furthermore, BGP-CT offers two
      flavors for per-prefix label allocation. The first flavor assigns a
      label for each unique "RD, EP". The second flavor assigns a label for
      each unique "Transport Class, EP" while ignoring the RD.</t>

      <t>The impacts on control plane and forwarding behavior for the above
      modes are detailed with an example in <xref target="CTRouteVis">Managing
      Transport Route Visibility</xref></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Comparison with other families using RFC-8277 encoding">
      <t>SAFI 128 (Inet-VPN) is an RFC8277 encoded family that carries service
      prefixes in the NLRI, where the prefixes come from the customer
      namespaces and are contexualized into separate user virtual service RIBs
      called VRFs using RFC4364 procedures.</t>

      <t>SAFI 4 (BGP LU) is an RFC8277 encoded family that carries transport
      prefixes in the NLRI, where the prefixes come from the provider
      namespace.</t>

      <t>SAFI 76 (Classful Transport) is an RFC8277 encoded family that
      carries transport prefixes in the NLRI, where the prefixes come from the
      provider namespace and are contexualized into separate Transport Route
      Databases using RFC4364 procedures.</t>

      <t>It is worth noting that SAFI 128 has been used to carry transport
      prefixes in "L3VPN Inter-AS Carrier's carrier" scenario, where BGP
      LU/LDP prefixes in CsC VRF are advertised in SAFI 128 towards the
      remote-end client carrier.</t>

      <t>In this document a new AFI/SAFI is used instead of reusing SAFI 128
      to carry these transport routes because it is operationally advantageous
      to segregate transport and service prefixes into separate address
      families. E.g. It allows to safely enable "per-prefix" label allocation
      scheme for Classful Transport prefixes without affecting SAFI 128
      service prefixes which may have huge scale. The "per prefix" label
      allocation scheme keeps the routing churn local during topology
      changes.</t>

      <t>A new family also facilitates having a different readvertisement path
      of the transport family routes in a network than the service route
      readvertisement path. Service routes (Inet-VPN) are exchanged over an
      EBGP multihop session between Autonomous systems with nexthop unchanged;
      whereas Classful Transport routes are readvertised over EBGP single hop
      sessions with "nexthop self" rewrite over inter-AS links.</t>

      <t>The Classful Transport family is similar in vein to BGP LU, in that
      it carries transport prefixes. The only difference is that it also
      carries in Route Target, an indication of which Transport Class the
      transport prefix belongs to and uses RD to disambiguate multiple
      instances of the same transport prefix in a BGP Update.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Procedures">
      <t>This section summarizes the procedures followed by various nodes
      speaking Classful Transport family.</t>

      <section title="Preparing the network to deploy Classful Transport planes">
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>Operator decides on the Transport Classes that exist in the
            network and allocates a Transport Class Route Target to identify
            each Transport Class.</t>

            <t>Operator configures Transport Classes on the SNs and BNs in the
            network with Transport Class Route Targets and unique
            Route-Distinguishers.</t>

            <t>Implementations MAY provide automatic generation and assignment
            of RD, RT values; they MAY also provide a way to manually override
            the automatic mechanism in order to deal with any conflicts that
            may arise with existing RD, RT values in different network domains
            participating in the deployment.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Origination of Classful Transport route">
        <t>
          <list>
            <t>At the ingress node of the tunnel's home domain, the tunneling
            protocols install tunnel ingress routes in the Transport Route
            Database associated with the Transport Class the tunnel belongs
            to.</t>

            <t>The egress node of the tunnel i.e. the tunnel endpoint
            originates the BGP Classful Transport route with NLRI containing
            RD:TunnelEndpoint, Transport Class RT and PNH TunnelEndpoint,
            which will resolve over the tunnel route in Transport Route
            Database at the ingress node. When the tunnel is up, the Classful
            Transport BGP route will become usable and get re-advertised.</t>

            <t>Alternatively, the ingress node may advertise this tunnel
            destination into BGP as a Classful Transport family route with
            NLRI RD:TunnelEndpoint, attaching a 'Transport Class' Route Target
            that identifies the Transport Class. This BGP CT route is
            advertised to EBGP peers and IBGP peers in neighboring domains.
            This route SHOULD NOT be advertised to the IBGP core that contains
            the tunnel.</t>

            <t>Unique RD SHOULD be used by the originator of a Classful
            Transport route to disambiguate the multiple BGP advertisements
            for a transport end point.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Ingress node receiving Classful Transport route">
        <list>
          <t>On receiving a BGP Classful Transport route with a PNH that is
          not directly connected (e.g. an IBGP-route), a Mapping Community on
          the route (the Transport Class RT) indicates which Transport Class
          this route maps to. The routes in the associated Transport Route
          Database are used to resolve the received PNH. If there does not
          exist a route in the Transport Route Database matching the PNH, the
          Classful Transport route is considered unusable and MUST NOT be
          advertised further.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Border node readvertising Classful Transport route with nexthop       self">
        <list>
          <t>The BN allocates an MPLS label to advertise upstream in Classful
          Transport NLRI. The BN also installs an MPLS route for that label
          that swaps the incoming label with a label received from the
          downstream BGP speaker or pops the incoming label. It then pushes
          received traffic to the transport tunnel or direct interface that
          the Classful Transport route's PNH resolved over.</t>

          <t>The label SHOULD be allocated with "per-prefix" label allocation
          semantics. RD is stripped from the BGP CT NLRI prefix when a BGP CT
          route is added to a Transport Route Database. The IP prefix in the
          Transport Route Database context (Transport-Class, IP-prefix) is
          used as the key to do per-prefix label allocation. This helps in
          avoiding BGP CT route churn through out the CT network when a
          failure happens in a domain. The failure is not propagated further
          than the BN closest to the failure.</t>

          <t>The value of advertised MPLS label is locally significant, and is
          dynamic by default. The BN may provide option to allocate a value
          from a statically carved out range. This can be achieved using
          locally configured export policy, or via mechanisms described in
          <xref target="RFC8669">BGP Prefix-SID</xref>.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Border node receiving Classful Transport route on EBGP">
        <list>
          <t>If the route is received with PNH that is known to be directly
          connected (e.g. EBGP single-hop peering address), the directly
          connected interface is checked for MPLS forwarding capability. No
          other nexthop resolution process is performed as the inter-AS link
          can be used for any Transport Class.</t>

          <t>If the inter-AS links should honor Transport Class, then the BN
          SHOULD follow procedures of an Ingress node described above and
          perform nexthop resolution process. The interface routes SHOULD be
          installed in the Transport Route Database belonging to the
          associated Transport Class.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Avoiding path-hiding through Route Reflectors">
        <list>
          <t>When multiple BNs exist such that theu advertise a RD:EP prefix
          to RRs, the RRs may hide all but one of the BNs, unless <xref
          target="RFC7911">ADDPATH</xref> is used for the Classful Transport
          family. This is similar to L3VPN option-B scenarios. Hence ADDPATH
          SHOULD be used for Classful Transport family, to avoid path-hiding
          through RRs.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Avoiding loop between Route Reflectors in forwarding path">
        <list>
          <t>Pair of redundant ABRs, each acting as an RR with nexthop self
          may chose each other as best path instead of the upstream ASBR,
          causing a traffic forwarding loop.</t>

          <t>Implementations SHOULD provide a way to alter the tie-breaking
          rule specified in <xref target="RFC4456">BGP RR</xref> to tie-break
          on CLUSTER_LIST step before ROUTER-ID step, when performing path
          selection for BGP CT routes. RFC4456 considers pure RR which is not
          in forwarding path. When RR is in forwarding path and reflects
          routes with nexthop self as is the case for ABR BNs in a BGP
          transport network, this rule may cause loops. This document suggests
          the following modification to the BGP Decision Process Tie Breaking
          rules (Sect. 9.1.2.2, <xref target="RFC4271"/>) when doing path
          selection for BGP CT family routes:</t>

          <t>The following rule SHOULD be inserted between Steps e) and f): a
          BGP Speaker SHOULD prefer a route with the shorter CLUSTER_LIST
          length. The CLUSTER_LIST length is zero if a route does not carry
          the CLUSTER_LIST attribute.</t>

          <t>Some deployment considerations can also help in avoiding this
          problem: <list>
              <t>IGP metric should be assigned such that "ABR to redundant
              ABR" cost is inferior than "ABR to upstream ASBR" cost.</t>

              <t>Tunnels belonging to non best effort Transport Classes SHOULD
              NOT be provisioned between ABRs. This will ensure that the route
              received from an ABR with nexthop self will not be usable at a
              redundant ABR.</t>
            </list> This avoids possibility of such loops altogether.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Ingress node receiving service route with Mapping Community">
        <list>
          <t>Service routes received with Mapping Community resolve using
          Transport Route Databases determined by the Resolution Scheme. If
          the resolution process does not find a Tunnel Ingress Route in any
          of the Transport Route Databases, the service route MUST be
          considered unusable for forwarding purpose and be withdrawn.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Coordinating between domains using different community       namespaces">
        <list>
          <t>Cooperating option-C domains may sometimes not agree on RT, RD,
          Mapping-community or Transport Route Target values because of
          differences in community namespaces (e.g. during network mergers or
          renumbering for expansion). Such deployments may deploy mechanisms
          to map and rewrite the Route Target values on domain boundaries,
          using per ASBR import policies. This is no different than any other
          BGP VPN family. Mechanisms used in inter-AS VPN deployments may be
          used with the Classful Transport family also.</t>

          <t>The Resolution Schemes SHOULD allow association with multiple
          Mapping Communities. This helps with renumbering, network mergers or
          transitions.</t>

          <t>Deploying unique RDs is strongly RECOMMENDED because it helps in
          troubleshooting by uniquely identifying originator of a route and
          avoids path-hiding.</t>

          <t>This document defines a new format of Route-Target
          extended-community to carry Transport Class, this avoids collision
          with regular Route Target namespace used by service routes.</t>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Flowspec Redirect to IP">
      <t>Flowspec routes using Redirect to IP nexthop is described in <xref
      target="FLOWSPEC-REDIR-IP">BGP Flow-Spec Redirect to IP
      Action</xref></t>

      <t>Such Flowspec BGP routes with Redirect to IP nexthop can be attached
      with a Mapping Community (e.g. Color:0:100), which allows redirecting
      the flow traffic over a tunnel to the IP nexthop satisfying the desired
      SLA (e.g. Transport Class color 100).</t>

      <t>Flowspec BGP family acts as just another service that can make use of
      BGP CT architecture to achieve Flow based forwarding with SLAs.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="BGP CT Egress TE">
      <t>Mechanisms described in <xref target="BGP-LU-EPE">BGP LU EPE</xref>
      also applies to BGP CT family.</t>

      <t>The Peer/32 or Peer/128 EPE route MAY be originated in BGP CT family
      with appropriate Mapping Community (e.g. transport-target:0:100), thus
      allowing an EPE path to the peer that satisfies the desired SLA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Interaction with BGP attributes specifying nexthop address and color">
      <t>The Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute described in <xref
      target="RFC9012">RFC9012</xref> can be used to request a specific type
      of tunnel encapsulation. Usage of this attribute may apply to BGP
      service routes or transport routes, including BGP Classful Transport
      family routes.</t>

      <t>Mechanisms described in <xref target="MULTI-NH-ATTR">BGP MultiNexthop
      Attribute</xref> allow a BGP route to carry multiple nexthop addresses.
      It also allows specifying 'Transport Class ID' as a qualifier for each
      Nexthop address.</t>

      <t>It should be noted that in such cases "Transport Class/Color" can
      exist in multiple places on the same route, and a precedence order needs
      to be established to determine which Transport class the route's nexthop
      should resolve over. This document suggests the following order of
      precedence, more preferred first: <list>
          <t>Transport Class ID SubTLV, in MultiNexthop Attribute.</t>

          <t>Color SubTLV, in Tunnel Encapsulation Attribute.</t>

          <t>Transport Target Extended community, on BGP CT route.</t>

          <t>Color Extended community, on BGP service route.</t>
        </list> The above precedence order follows more specific scoping of
      Color to less specific scoping.</t>

      <t>Transport Class ID specified for Nexthop-Leg subTLV in a MultiNextHop
      attribute is more specific indication of Color than Color subTLV in a
      TEA, which inturn is more specific than Mapping Community (Transport
      Target) on a BGP CT transport route, which is inturn more specific than
      a Service route scoped Mapping Community (Color Extended community).</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Scaling considerations">
      <section title="Avoiding unintended spread of BGP CT routes across domains">
        <list>
          <t><xref target="RFC8212">RFC8212</xref> suggests BGP speakers
          require explicit configuration of both BGP Import and Export
          Policies in order to receive or send routes over EBGP sessions.</t>

          <t>It is recommended to follow this for BGP CT routes. It will
          prohibit unintended advertisement of transport routes throughout the
          BGP CT transport domain which may span across multiple AS domains.
          This will conserve usage of MPLS label and nexthop resources in the
          network. An ASBR of a domain can be provisioned to allow routes with
          only the Transport Route Targets that are required by SNs in the
          domain.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Constrained distribution of PNHs to SNs (On Demand Nexthop)">
        <list>
          <t>This section describes how the number of Protocol Nexthops
          advertised to a SN or BN can be constrained using BGP Classsful
          Transport and <xref target="RFC4684">Route Target
          Constraints</xref>.</t>

          <t>An egress SN MAY advertise BGP CT route for RD:eSN with two Route
          Targets: transport-target:0:&lt;TC&gt; and a RT carrying
          &lt;eSN&gt;:&lt;TC&gt;. Where TC is the Transport Class identifier,
          and eSN is the IP-address used by SN as BGP nexthop in its service
          route advertisements.</t>

          <t>Note that such use of the IP address specific route target
          &lt;eSN&gt;:&lt;TC&gt; is optional in a BGP CT network. It is
          required only if there is a requirement to prune the propagation of
          the transport route for an egress node eSN to only the set of
          ingress nodes that need it.</t>

          <t>The transport-target:0:&lt;TC&gt; is the new type of route target
          (Transport Class RT) defined in this document. It is carried in BGP
          extended community attribute (BGP attribute code 16).</t>

          <t>The RT carrying &lt;eSN&gt;:&lt;TC&gt; MAY be an IP-address
          specific regular RT (BGP attribute code 16), IPv6-address specific
          RT (BGP attribute code 25), or a Wide-communities based RT (BGP
          attribute code 34) as described in <xref target="RTC-Ext">Route
          Target Constrain Extension</xref>. This document recommends using
          Wide-communities based RT for the same.</t>

          <t>An ingress SN MAY import BGP CT routes with Route Target carrying
          &lt;eSN&gt;:&lt;TC&gt;. The ingress SN MAY learn the eSN values
          either by configuration, or it MAY discover them from the BGP
          nexthop field in the BGP VPN service routes received from eSN. A BGP
          ingress SN receiving a BGP service route with nexthop of eSN SHOULD
          generate a RTC/Extended-RTC route for Route Target prefix &lt;Origin
          ASN&gt;:&lt;eSN&gt;/[80|176] in order to learn BGP CT transport
          routes to reach eSN. This allows constrained distribution of the
          transport routes to the PNHs actually required by iSN.</t>

          <t>When path of route propogation of BGP CT routes is same as the
          RTC routes, a BN would learn the RTC routes advertised by ingress
          SNs and propagate further. This will allow constraining distribution
          of BGP CT routes for a PNH to only the necessary BNs in the network,
          closer to the egress SN.</t>

          <t>This mechanism provides "On Demand Nexthop" of BGP CT routes,
          which help with the scaling of MPLS forwarding state at SN and
          BN.</t>

          <t>However, the amount of state carried in RTC family may become
          proportional to number of PNHs in the network. To strike a balance,
          the RTC route advertisements for &lt;Origin
          ASN&gt;:&lt;eSN&gt;/[80|176] MAY be confined to the BNs in home
          region of ingress-SN, or the BNs of a super core.</t>

          <t>Such a BN in the core of the network SHOULD import BGP CT routes
          with Transport-Target:0:&lt;TC&gt; and generate a RTC route for
          &lt;Origin ASN&gt;:0:&lt;TC&gt;/96, while not propagating the more
          specific RTC requests for specific PNHs. This will let the BN learn
          transport routes to all eSN nodes. But confine their propagation to
          ingress-SNs.</t>
        </list>
      </section>

      <section title="Limiting scope of visibility of PE loopback as PNHs">
        <list>
          <t>It may be even more desirable to limit the number of PNHs that
          are globaly visible in the network. This is possible using mechanism
          described in <xref target="MPLS-NAMESPACES">MPLS
          Namespaces</xref></t>

          <t>Such that advertisement of PE loopback addresses as next-hop in
          BGP service routes is confined to the region they belong to. An
          anycast IP-address called "Context Protocol Nexthop Address" (CPNH)
          abstracts the SNs in a region from other regions in the network,
          swapping the SN scoped service label with a CPNH scoped private
          namespace label.</t>

          <t>This provides much greater advantage in terms of scaling and
          convergence. Changes to implement this feature are required only on
          the local region's BNs and RRs.</t>
        </list>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="OAM considerations">
      <t>Standard MPLS OAM procedures specified in <xref target="RFC8029"/>
      also apply to BGP Classful Transport.</t>

      <t>The 'Target FEC Stack' sub-TLV for IPv4 Classful Transport has a
      Sub-Type of [TBD], and a length of 13. The Value field consists of the
      RD advertised with the Classful Transport prefix, the IPv4 prefix (with
      trailing 0 bits to make 32 bits in all) and a prefix length encoded as
      follows:</t>

      <figure anchor="FECv4" title="Classful Transport IPv4 FEC">
        <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                      Route Distinguisher                      |
      |                          (8 octets)                           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                         IPv4 prefix                           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      | Prefix Length |                 Must Be Zero                  |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	</artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>The 'Target FEC Stack' sub-TLV for IPv6 Classful Transport has a
      Sub-Type of [TBD], and a length of 25. The Value field consists of the
      RD advertised with the Classful Transport prefix, the IPv6 prefix (with
      trailing 0 bits to make 128 bits in all) and a prefix length encoded as
      follows:</t>

      <figure anchor="FECv6" title="Classful Transport IPv6 FEC">
        <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
       0                   1                   2                   3
       0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                      Route Distinguisher                      |
      |                          (8 octets)                           |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      |                         IPv6 prefix                           |
      |                                                               |
      |                                                               |
      |                                                               |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
      | Prefix Length |                 Must Be Zero                  |
      +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
	</artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title="Applicability to Network Slicing">
      <t>In Network Slicing, the Transport Slice Controller (TSC) sets up the
      Topology (e.g. RSVP-TE, SR-TE tunnels with desired characteristics) and
      resources (e.g. polices/shapers) in a transport network to create a
      Transport Slice. The Transport Class construct described in this
      document represents the "Topology Slice" portion of this equation.</t>

      <t>The TSC can use the Transport Class Identifier (Color value) to
      provision a transport tunnel in a specific Topology Slice.</t>

      <t>Further, Network Slice Controller can use the Mapping Community on
      the service route to map traffic to the desired Transport Slice.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="SRv6 support">
      <t> natv text </t>

      <t>This section describes how BGP CT may be used to set up inter domain
      tunnels of a certain Transport Class, when using Segment Routing over
      IPv6 (SRv6) data plane on the inter AS links or as an intra AS tunneling
      mechanism.</t>

      <t><xref target="RFC8986"/> specifies the SRv6 Endpoint behaviors (End
      USD, End.BM, End.B6.Encaps and End.Replace, End.ReplaceB6,
      respectively). <xref target="SRV6-INTER-DOMAIN"/> specify the SRv6
      Endpoint behaviors (END.REPLACE, END.REPLACEB6 and END.DB6). These are
      leveraged for BGP CT with SRv6 data plane.</t>

      <t>The BGP Classful Transport route update for SRv6 MUST include the BGP
      Prefix-SID attribute along with SRv6 SID information as specified in
      <xref target="SRV6-SERVICES"/>. It may also include SRv6 SID structure
      for Transposition as specified in <xref target="SRV6-SERVICES"/>. It
      should be noted that prefixes carried in BGP CT family are transport
      layer end-points, e.g. PE loopback addresses. Thus the SRv6 SID carried
      in a BGP CT route is also a transport layer identifier.</t>

      <t>This document extends the usage of "SRv6 label route tunnel" TLV to
      AFI=1/2 SAFI 76. "SRv6 label route tunnel" is the TLV of the BGP
      Prefix-SID Attribute as specified in <xref
      target="SRV6-MPLS-AGRWL"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="CTProc"
             title="Illustration of BGP CT procedures in Inter AS option-C">
      <section title="Topology">
        <figure anchor="RDLabelVisibility" title="Multi-Domain BGP CT Network">
          <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">

                [RR26]      [RR27]                       [RR16]
                 |            |                             |
                 |            |                             |
                 |+-[ABR23]--+|+--[ASBR21]---[ASBR13]-+|+--[PE11]--+
                 ||          |||          `  /        |||          |
[CE41]--[PE25]--[P28]       [P29]          `/        [P15]     [CE31]
                 |           | |           /`         | |          |
                 |           | |          /  `        | |          |
                 |           | |         /    `       | |          |
                 +--[ABR24]--+ +--[ASBR22]---[ASBR14]-+ +--[PE12]--+
                                                                                 

       |                |                  |                    |
       +                +                  +                    +
    CE |     region-1   |   region-2       |                    |CE
   AS4              ...AS2...                       AS1          AS3

41.41.41.41  ------------ Traffic Direction ----------&gt;   31.31.31.31
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>This example shows a provider network that comprises of two
        Autonomous systems, AS1, AS2. They are serving customers AS3, AS4
        respectively. Traffic direction being described is CE41 to CE31. CE31
        may request a specific SLA (e.g. Gold for this traffic), when
        traversing these provider networks.</t>

        <t>AS2 is further divided into two regions. So, there are three tunnel
        domains in provider space. AS1 uses ISIS Flex-Algo intra-domain
        tunnels, whereas AS2 uses RSVP-TE intra-domain tunnels.</t>

        <t>The network has two Transport classes: Gold with transport class id
        100, Bronze with transport class id 200. These transport classes are
        provisioned at the PEs and the Border nodes (ABRs, ASBRs) in the
        network.</t>

        <t>Following tunnels exist for Gold transport class.<list>
            <t>PE25_to_ABR23_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>PE25_to_ABR24_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>ABR23_to_ASBR22_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>ASBR13_to_PE11_gold - ISIS FlexAlgo tunnel</t>

            <t>ASBR14_to_PE11_gold - ISIS FlexAlgo tunnel</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Following tunnels exist for Bronze transport class.<list>
            <t>PE25_to_ABR23_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>ABR23_to_ASBR21_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>ABR23_to_ASBR22_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>ABR24_to_ASBR21_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

            <t>ASBR13_to_PE12_bronze - ISIS FlexAlgo tunnel</t>

            <t>ASBR14_to_PE11_bronze - ISIS FlexAlgo tunnel</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>These tunnels are either provisioned or auto-discovered to belong
        to transport class 100 or 200.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Service Layer route exchange">
        <t>Service nodes PE11, PE12 negotiate service families (SAFIs 1, 128)
        on the BGP session with RR16. Service helpers RR16 and RR26 exchange
        these service routes with nexthop unchanged over a multihop EBGP
        session between the two AS. PE25 negotiates service families (SAFIs 1,
        128) with RR26.</t>

        <t>The PEs see each other as nexthop in the BGP Update for service
        family (SAFIs 1, 128) routes. Addpath send, receive is enabled on both
        directions on the EBGP multihop session between RR16 and RR26 for
        SAFIs 1, 128. Addpath send is negotiated in the RR to PE direction in
        each AS. This is to avoid path hiding of service routes at RR. E.g.
        SAFI 1 routes advertised by both PE11 and PE12. Or, SAFI 128 routes
        originated by both PE11 and PE12 using same RD.</t>

        <t>Forwarding happens using service routes installed at service nodes
        PE25, PE11, PE12 only. Service routes received from CEs are not
        present in any other nodes' FIB in the network.</t>

        <t>As an example, CE31 advertises a route for prefix 31.31.31.31 with
        nexthop as self to PE11, PE12. CE31 can attach a Mapping Community
        Color:0:100 on this route, to indicate its request for Gold SLA. Or,
        PE11 can attach the same using locally configured policies.</t>

        <t>Consider CE31 is getting VPN service from PE11. The RD1:31.31.31.31
        route is readvertised in SAFI 128 by PE11 with nexthop self (1.1.1.1)
        and label V-L1, to RR16 with the Mapping Community Color:0:100
        attached. RR16 advertises this route with Addpath-ID to RR26 which
        readvertises to PE25 with nexthop unchanged. Now PE25 can resolve the
        PNH 1.1.1.1 using transport routes received in BGP CT or BGP LU.</t>

        <t>Using Addpath, service routes advertised by PE11 and PE12 for SAFIs
        1, 128 reach PE25 via RR16, RR26 with the nexthop unchanged, as PE11
        or PE12. </t>

        <t>The IP FIB at PE25 VRF will have a route for 31.31.31.31 with a
        nexthop when resolved, that points to a Gold tunnel in ingress
        domain.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Transport Layer route propagation">
        <t>Egress nodes PE11, PE12 negotiate BGP CT family with transport
        ASBRs ASBR13, ASBR14. These egress nodes originate BGP CT routes for
        tunnel endpoint addresses, that are advertised as nexthop in BGP
        service routes. In this example both PEs participate in transport
        classes Gold and Bronze. The protocol procedures are explained using
        Gold SLA plane and the Bronze SLA plane is used to highlight the path
        hiding aspects.</t>

        <t>PE11 is provisioned with transport class 100, RD value 1.1.1.1:10
        and a transport-target:0:100 for Gold tunnels. And a Transport class
        200 with RD value 1.1.1.1:20, and transport route target 0:200 for
        Bronze tunnels. Similarly, PE12 is provisioned with transport class
        100, RD value 1.1.1.2:10 and a transport-target:0:100 for Gold
        tunnels. And transport class 200, RD value 1.1.1.2:20 with
        transport-target:0:200 for Bronze tunnels. Note that in this example
        the BGP CT routes carry only the transport class route target, and no
        IP address format route target.</t>

        <t>The RD value originated by an egress node is not modified by any
        BGP speakers when the route is readvertised to the ingress node. Thus
        the RD can be used to identify the originator (unique RD provisioned)
        or set of originators (RD reused on multiple nodes).</t>

        <t>Similarly, these transport classes are also configured on ASBRs,
        ABRs and PEs with same Transport Route Target and unique RDs.</t>

        <t>ASBR13 and ASBR14 negotiate BGP CT family with transport ASBRs
        ASBR21, ASBR22 in neighboring AS. They negotiate BGP CT family with
        RR27 in region 2, which reflects BGP CT routes to ABR23, ABR24. ABR23,
        ABR24 negotiate BGP CT family with Ingress node PE25 in region 1. BGP
        LU family is also negotiated on these sessions alongside BGP CT
        family. BGP LU carries "best effort" transport class routes, BGP CT
        carries gold, bronze transport class routes.</t>

        <t>PE11 is provisioned to originate BGP CT route with Gold SLA to
        endpoint PE11. This route is sent with NLRI RD prefix
        1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1, Label B-L0, nexthop 1.1.1.1 and a route target
        extended community transport-target:0:100. Label B-L0 can either be
        Implicit Null (Label 3) or a Ultimate Hop Pop (UHP) label.</t>

        <t>This route is received by ASBR13 and it resolves over the tunnel
        ASBR13_to_PE11_gold. The route is then readvertised by ASBR13 in BGP
        CT family to ASBRs ASBR21, ASBR22 according to export policy. This
        route is sent with same NLRI RD prefix 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1, Label B-L1,
        nexthop self, and transport-target:0:100. MPLS swap route is installed
        at ASBR13 for B-L1 with a nexthop pointing to ASBR13_to_PE11_gold
        tunnel.</t>

        <t>Similarly ASBR14 also receives BGP CT route for 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1
        from PE11 and it resolves over the tunnel ASBR14_to_PE11_gold. The
        route is then readvertised by ASBR14 in BGP CT family to ASBRs ASBR21,
        ASBR22 according to export policy. This route is sent with same NLRI
        RD prefix 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1, Label B-L2, nexthop self, and
        transport-target:0:100. MPLS swap route is installed at ASBR14 for
        B-L1 with a nexthop pointing to ASBR14_to_PE11_gold tunnel.</t>

        <t>In the Bronze plane, BGP CT route with Bronze SLA to endpoint PE11
        is originated by PE11 with a NLRI containing RD prefix
        1.1.1.1:20:1.1.1.1, and appropriate label. The RD allows both Gold and
        Bronze advertisements traverse path selection pinchpoints without any
        path hiding at RRs or ASBRs. And route target extended community
        transport-target:0:200 lets the route resolve over Bronze tunnels in
        the network, similar to the process being described for Gold SLA
        path.</t>

        <t>Moving back to the Gold plane, ASBR21 receives the Gold SLA BGP CT
        routes for NLRI RD prefix 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 over the single hop EBGP
        sessions from ASBR13, ASBR14, and can compute ECMP/FRR towards them.
        ASBR21 readvertises BGP CT route for 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 with nexthop
        self (loopback adderss 2.2.2.1) to RR27, advertising a new label B-L3.
        MPLS swap route is installed for label B-L3 at ASBR21 to swap to
        received label B-L1, B-L2 and forward to ASBR13, ASBR14 respectively.
        RR27 readvertises this BGP CT route to ABR23, ABR24 with label and
        nexthop unchanged.</t>

        <t>Similarly, ASBR22 receives BGP CT route 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 over the
        single hop EBGP sessions from ASBR13, ASBR14, and readvertises with
        nexthop self (loopback adderss 2.2.2.2) to RR27, advertising a new
        label B-L4. MPLS swap route is installed for label B-L4 at ASBR22 to
        swap to received label B-L1, B-L2 and forward to ASBR13, ASBR14
        respectively. RR27 readvertises this BGP CT route also to ABR23, ABR24
        with label and nexthop unchanged.</t>

        <t>Addpath is enabled for BGP CT family on the sessions between RR27
        and ASBRs, ABRs such that routes for 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 with the
        nexthops ASBR21 and ASBR22 are reflected to ABR23, ABR24 without any
        path hiding. Thus giving ABR23 visibiity of both available nexthops
        for Gold SLA.</t>

        <t>ABR23 receives the route with nexthop 2.2.2.1, label B-L3 from
        RR27. The route target "transport-target:0:100" on this route acts as
        Mapping Community, and instructs ABR23 to strictly resolve the nexthop
        using transport class 100 routes only. ABR23 is unable to find a route
        for 2.2.2.1 with transport class 100. Thus it considers this route
        unusable and does not propagate it further. This prunes ASBR21 from
        Gold SLA tunneled path.</t>

        <t>ABR23 also receives the route with nexthop 2.2.2.2, label B-L4 from
        RR27. The route target "transport-target:0:100" on this route acts as
        Mapping Community, and instructs ABR23 to strictly resolve the nexthop
        using transport class 100 routes only. ABR23 successfully resolves the
        nexthop to point to ABR23_to_ASBR22_gold tunnel. ABR23 readvertises
        this BGP CT route with nexthop self (loopback address 2.2.2.3) and a
        new label B-L5 to PE25. Swap route for B-L5 is installed by ABR23 to
        swap to label B-L4, and forward into ABR23_to_ASBR22_gold tunnel.</t>

        <t>PE25 receives the BGP CT route for prefix 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 with
        label B-L5, nexthop 2.2.2.3 and transport-target:0:100 from RR26. And
        it similarly resolves the nexthop 2.2.2.3 over transport class 100,
        pushing labels associated with PE25_to_ABR23_gold tunnel.</t>

        <t>In this manner, the Gold transport LSP "ASBR13_to_PE11_gold" in
        egress-domain is extended by BGP CT until the ingress-node PE25 in
        ingress domain, to create an end-to-end Gold SLA path. MPLS swap
        routes are installed at ASBR13, ASBR22 and ABR23, when propagating the
        PE11 BGP CT Gold transport class route 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 with nexthop
        self towards PE25.</t>

        <t>The BGP CT LSP thus formed, originates in PE25, and terminates in
        ASBR13 (assuming PE11 advertised Implicit Null), traversing over the
        Gold underlay LSPs in each domain. ASBR13 uses UHP to stitch the BGP
        CT LSP into the "ASBR13_to_PE11_gold" LSP to traverse the last domain,
        thus satisfying Gold SLA end-to-end.</t>

        <t>When PE25 receives service routes from RR26 with nexthop 1.1.1.1
        and mapping community Color:0:100, it resolves over this BGP CT route
        1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1. Thus pushing label B-L5, and pushing as top label
        the labels associated with PE25_to_ABR23_gold tunnel.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Data plane view">
        <section title="Steady state">
          <t>This section describes how the data plane looks like in steady
          state.</t>

          <t>CE41 transmits an IP packet with destination as 31.31.31.31. On
          receiving this packet PE25 performs a lookup in the IP FIB
          associated with the CE41 interface. This lookup yeids the service
          route that pushes the VPN service label V-L1, BGP CT label B-L5, and
          labels for PE25_to_ABR23_gold tunnel. Thus PE25 encapsulates the IP
          packet in MPLS packet with label V-L1(innermost), B-L5, and top
          label as PE25_to_ABR23_gold tunnel. This MPLS packet is thus
          transmitted to ABR23 using Gold SLA.</t>

          <t>ABR23 decapsulates the packet received on PE25_to_ABR23_gold
          tunnel as required, and finds the MPLS packet with label B-L5. It
          performs lookup for label B-L5 in the global MPLS FIB. This yields
          the route that swaps label B-L5 with label B-L4, and pushes top
          label provided by ABR23_to_ASBR22_gold tunnel. Thus ABR23 transmits
          the MPLS packet with label B-L4 to ASBR22, on a tunnel that
          satisfies Gold SLA.</t>

          <t>ASBR22 similarly performs a lookup for label B-L4 in global MPLS
          FIB, finds the route that swaps label B-L4 with label B-L2, and
          forwards to ASBR13 over the directly connected MPLS enabled
          interface. This interface is a common resource not dedicated to any
          specific transport class, in this example.</t>

          <t>ASBR13 receives the MPLS packet with label B-L2, and performs a
          lookup in MPLS FIB, finds the route that pops label B-L2, and pushes
          labels associated with ASBR13_to_PE11_gold tunnel. This transmits
          the MPLS packet with VPN label V-L1 to PE11 using a tunnel that
          preserves Gold SLA in AS 1.</t>

          <t>PE11 receives the MPLS packet with V-L1, and performs VPN
          forwarding. Thus transmitting the original IP payload from CE41 to
          CE31. The payload has traversed path satisfying Gold SLA
          end-to-end.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Local repair of primary path">
          <t>This section describes how the data plane at ASBR22 reacts when
          link between ASBR22 and ASBR13 experiences a failure, and an
          alternate path exists.</t>

          <t>Assuming ASBR22_to_ASBR13 link goes down, such that traffic with
          Gold SLA going to PE11 needs repair. ASBR22 has an alternate BGP CT
          route for 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 from ASBR14. This has been
          preprogrammed in forwarding by ASBR22 as FRR backup nexthop for
          label B-L4. This allows the Gold SLA traffic to be locally repaired
          at ASBR22 without the failure event propagated in the BGP CT
          network. In this case, ingress node PE25 will not know there was a
          failure, and traffic restoration will be independent of prefix scale
          (PIC).</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Absorbing failure of primary path. Fallback to best-effort tunnels.">
          <t>This section describes how the data plane reacts when gold path
          experiences a failure, but no alternate path exists.</t>

          <t>Assuming tunnel ABR23_to_ASBR22_gold goes down, such that now
          end-to-end Gold path does not exist in the network. This makes the
          BGP CT route for RD prefix 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 unusable at ABR23.
          This makes ABR23 send a BGP withdrawal for 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 to
          PE25.</t>

          <t>Withdrawal for 1.1.1.1:10:1.1.1.1 allows PE25 to react to the
          loss of gold path to 1.1.1.1. Assuming PE25 is provisioned to use
          best-effort transport class as the backup path, this withdrawal of
          BGP CT route allows PE25 to adjust the nexthop of the VPN
          Service-route to push the labels provided by the BGP LU route. That
          repairs the traffic to go via best effort path. PE25 can also be
          provisioned to use Bronze transport class as the backup path. The
          repair will happen in similar manner in that case as-well.</t>

          <t>Traffic repair to absorb the failure happens at ingress node
          PE25, in a service prefix scale independent manner. This is called
          PIC (Prefix scale Independent Convergence). The repair time will be
          proportional to time taken for withdrawing the BGP CT route.</t>

          <t>The above examples demostrate the various levels of failsafe
          mechanisms available to protect traffic in a BGP CT network.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Deployment considerations.">
      <t> reshma and natv text </t>

      <section anchor="CTRouteVis" title="Managing Transport Route Visibility">
        <t>This section details the usage of BGP-CT RD and label allocation
        modes to calibrate the level of path visibility and the amount of
        route churn in a multi-domain network.</t>

        <t>Consider a multi-domain BGP-CT network as illustrated in the figure
        below.</t>

        <figure anchor="MultiDomainNetwork" title="Multi-Domain Network">
          <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
       |-----AS3-----|  |-------AS1------|

                +--------ASBR11     +--PE11 (EP1)
                |              \   /
         +----ASBR31            (P)----PE12 (EP2)
         |      |              / | \
         |      +--------ASBR12  |  +--PE13 (EP3)
         |                       | 
         |                       +-----PE14 (EP4)
  PE31--(P)
         |        
         |       
         |      +--------ASBR21     +--PE21 (EP5)
         |      |              \   /
         +----ASBR32            (P)----PE22 (EP6)
                |              / | \
                +--------ASBR22  |  +--PE22 (EP7)
                                 |
                                 +-----PE24 (EP8)

       |-----AS3-----|  |-------AS2------|
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>The following table details the BGP-CT route and path visibility at
        PE31-- for each TC.</t>

        <figure anchor="RDLabelVis"
                title="Route and Path Visibility at Ingress Node">
          <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
      +--------+------+-------+-------+---------+---------+
      |EP-type |Origin|RD-Mode|PP-Mode|CT Routes|CT Labels|
      +--------+------+-------+-------+---------+---------+
      |Unicast |SN    |Unique |TC,EP  |    16   |    8    |
      |Unicast |SN    |Unique |RD,EP  |    16   |   16    |
      |Unicast |BN    |Unique |TC,EP  |    16   |    8    |
      |Unicast |BN    |Unique |RD,EP  |    16   |   16    |
      |--------|------|-------|-------|---------|---------|
      |Anycast |SN    |Unique |TC,EP  |    16   |    2    |
      |Anycast |SN    |Unique |RD,EP  |    16   |   16    |
      |Anycast |SN    |Same   |TC,EP  |     2   |    2    |
      |Anycast |SN    |Same   |RD,EP  |     2   |    2    |
      |Anycast |BN    |Unique |TC,EP  |     4   |    2    |
      |Anycast |BN    |Unique |RD,EP  |     4   |    4    |
      |Anycast |BN    |Same   |TC,EP  |     2   |    2    |
      |Anycast |BN    |Same   |RD,IP  |     2   |    2    |
      +--------+------+-------+-------+---------+---------+
</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>In the above example, both route churn and TE granularity are
        directly proportional to the number of CT labels received.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Managing Intent at Service and Transport layers.">
        <section title="Heterogenous Color domains.">
          <t>text</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Domains with non agreeing Color namespaces.">
          <t>text</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Illustration.">
          <t>Illustration of how Anycast and Unicast endpoints are deployed in
          Heterogenous color domains with non agreeing Color namespaces.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Migration scenarios.">
        <section title="BGP CT islands connected via BGP LU domain.">
          <t>This section explains how end-to-end SLA can be achieved while
          transiting a domain that does not support BGP-CT. BGP-LU is used in
          such domains to connect the BGP CT islands. </t>

          <figure anchor="BGPCTIsles"
                  title="BGP CT in AS1 and AS3 connected by BGP LU in AS2">
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
              +----------------EBGP-MHOP-CT-----------+
              |                                       |
        AS3   |                   AS2                 |   AS1
  [PE31-----ASBR31]--------[ASBR22---ASBR21]-------[ASBR11---PE11]

                 &lt;-EBGP-LU-&gt;              &lt;-EBGP-LU-&gt;
   &lt;---IBGP-CT---&gt;          &lt;---IBGP-LU---&gt;        &lt;---IBGP-CT---&gt;

            ---------Packet Forwarding Direction---------&gt;
 

</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>In the above topology there are three ASs. AS1 and AS3 supports
          BGP-CT. AS2 is a domain that does not support BGP CT.</t>

          <t>Nodes in AS1,AS2 and AS3 negotiate IBGP-LU within the domain.
          Nodes in AS1 and AS3 negotiate IBGP CT within the domain. ASBR11 and
          ASBR21 as well as ASBR22 and ASBR31 negotiate EBGP-LU over directly
          connected interdomain links. ASBR11 and ASBR31 have reachability to
          each other&#8217;s loopbacks through BGP-LU. ASBR11 and ASBR31
          negotiate BGP-CT over a multihop EBGP session formed using BGP-LU
          reachability.</t>

          <t>The following tunnels exist for Gold transport class<list>
              <t>PE11_to_ASBR11_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR11_to_PE11_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE31_to_ASBR31_gold - SRTE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR31_to_PE31_gold - SRTE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Bronze transport class<list>
              <t>PE11_to_ASBR11_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR11_to_PE11_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE31_to_ASBR31_bronze - SRTE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR31_to_PE31_bronze - SRTE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>These tunnels are provisioned to belong to transport class gold
          and bronze, and are advertised between ASBR31 and ASBR11 with
          Nexthop self.</t>

          <t>Further in AS2 the following tunnels exist to satisfy the
          different SLAs, using per SLA endpoint:<list>
              <t>ASBR21_to_ASBR22_lpbk_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR22_to_ASBR21_lpbk_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR21_to_ASBR22_lpbk_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR22_to_ASBR21_lpbk_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>RD:PE11 BGP CT route is originated from PE11 towards ASBR11 with
          transport-target gold. ASBR11 readvertises this route with Nexthop
          as SLA endpoint ASBR11_lpbk_gold on the EBGP CT MHOP session towards
          ASBR31. ASBR11 originates ASBR11_lpbk_gold in EBGP LU towards ABR21
          with gold SLA community. Similarily for ASBR11 originates per SLA
          loopback routes for each SLA it supports attaching the community for
          that SLA. This SLA community is used by ASBR31 to leak the LU routes
          into their respective CT TRDBs.</t>

          <t>ASBR21 readvertises the ASBR11_lpbk_gold BGP-LU route to ASBR22
          with the nexthop as a unique loopback (ASBR21_lpbk_gold)
          representing gold SLA. ASBR22 on receiving these endpoints resolve
          them over the appropriate SLA transport tunnels by virtue of per SLA
          tunnel endpoint provisioned in AS2. ASBR22, on succesful resolution,
          readvertises this BGP-LU routes to ASBR31 with nexthop self and a
          new label.</t>

          <t>ASBR31 imports ASBR11_lpbk_gold route received via EBGP-LU from
          ASBR22 to gold TRDB based on the received SLA community. ASBR31 uses
          this gold TRDB route to resolve the NH ASBR11_lpbk_gold of RD:PE11
          route received over the MHOP EBGP-MHOP-CT session with
          transport-target gold, thus preserving the end-to-end SLA. Now
          ASBR31 readvertises RD:PE11 route with nexthop as self thus
          stitching with the BGP-LU LSP. Intradomain traffic forwarding in AS1
          and AS3 follows the procedures as explained in <xref
          target="CTProc">Illustration of CT Procedures</xref></t>

          <t>In cases where an SLA cannot be preserved in AS2, it can be
          carried over available SLAs (ex: best-effort SLA) by rewriting the
          nexthop to ASBR21 loopback assigned to that endpoint. This eases
          migration in case of heterogenous color domains.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="BGP CT - Interop between MPLS and other forwarding technologies.">

          <t> This section describes how nodes supporting dissimilar encapsulation technologies
              interoperate with each other when using BGP CT family.</t>

          <section title="Interop between MPLS and SRv6 nodes.">
          <t> BGP speakers carry MPLS label and SRv6 SID in BGP CT SAFI 76 routes using 
           protocol encoding as described in <xref target="CTMultiEncap">Carrying Multiple Encapsulation information</xref> </t>
          <t> MPLS Labels are carried using RFC 8277 encoding, and SRv6 SID is carried 
          using Prefix SID attribute as specified in RFC 8986 </t>

          <figure anchor="BGPCT_MPLS_SRV6"
                  title="BGP CT Interop between MPLS and SRv6 nodes">
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">

                      RR1--+
                             \  +-------R2  [MPLS + SRv6]
                              \ |        
                      R1--------P-------R3  [MPLS only]
                [MPLS + SRv6]   |
                                +-------R4  [SRv6 only]

                  &lt;---- Bidirectional Traffic ----&gt;
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>This example shows a provider network with a mix of devices with different 
          forwarding capabilities. R1 and R2 support forwarding both MPLS and SRv6 packets. 
          R3 supports forwarding MPLS packets only. R4 supports forwarding SRv6 packets only. 
          All these nodes peer with Route Reflector RR1 which reflects routes between these nodes
          with nexthop unchanged.</t>

          <t>R1 and R2 send and receive both MPLS label and SRv6 SID in the BGP CT control plane 
           routes. This allows them to be ingress and egress for both MPLS and SRv6 data planes.
           MPLS Label is carried using RFC 8277 encoding, and SRv6 SID is carried using Prefix SID 
           attribute as specified in RFC 8986, without any transposition.</t>

          <t>R1 and R3 send and receive MPLS label in the BGP CT control plane routes using RFC 8277 
          encoding. This allows them to be ingress and egress for MPLS data plane. R1 will carry SRv6 SID 
          in Prefix-SID attribute, which will not be used by R3. In order to interoperate with MPLS only 
          device R3, R1 MUST NOT use SRv6 Transposition scheme described in RFC 8986 that overloads the 
          RFC 8277 MPLS-Label field with SRv6 Transposition information.</t>

          <t>R1 and R4 send and receive SRv6 SID in the BGP CT control plane routes using BGP Prefix-SID 
          attribute. This allows them to be ingress and egress for SRv6 data plane. R4 will carry MPLS-Label 
          3 (Implicit-NULL) in RFC 8277 encoding, which tells R1 not to push any MPLS label towards R4. The 
          MPLS Label advertised by R1 will not be used by R4. SRv6 forwarding will be used between 
          R1 and R4.</t>

          <t>Note in this example that R3 and R4 cannot communicate directly with each other, because they dont 
          support a common forwarding technology </t>
        </section>

          <section title="Interop between MPLS and IPIP nodes.">
          <t> MPLS Labels are carried using RFC 8277 encoding, and IPIP tunnel information is carried 
          using TEA attribute as specified in RFC 9012 </t>

          <figure anchor="BGPCT_MPLS_IPIP"
                  title="BGP CT Interop between MPLS and IPIP nodes.">
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">

                      RR1--+
                             \  +-------R2  [MPLS + IPIP]
                              \ |        
                      R1--------P-------R3  [MPLS only]
                [MPLS + IPIP]   |
                                +-------R4  [IPIP only]

                  &lt;---- Bidirectional Traffic ----&gt;
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>In this example, R1 and R2 support forwarding both MPLS and IPIP packets. R3 supports 
          forwarding MPLS packets only. R4 supports forwarding IPIP packets only. All these nodes peer 
          with Route Reflector RR1 which reflects routes between these nodes with nexthop unchanged.</t>

          <t>R1 and R2 send and receive both MPLS label and IPIP encap info in the BGP CT control plane 
           routes. This allows them to be ingress and egress for both MPLS and IPIP data planes.
           MPLS Label is carried using RFC 8277 encoding. IPIP information is carried using TEA 
           attribute as specified in RFC 9012.</t>

          <t>R1 and R3 send and receive MPLS label in the BGP CT control plane routes using RFC 8277 
          encoding. This allows them to be ingress and egress for MPLS data plane. R1 will carry IPIP 
          info in TEA attribute, which will not be used by R3. Only MPLS forwarding can be used between 
          R1 and R3.</t>

          <t>R1 and R4 send and receive IPIP info in the BGP CT control plane routes using BGP TEA attribute. 
          This allows them to be ingress and egress for IPIP data plane. R4 will carry MPLS-Label 
          3 (Implicit-NULL) in RFC 8277 encoding, which tells R1 not to push any MPLS label towards R4. The 
          MPLS Label advertised by R1 will not be used by R4. IPIP tunneled forwarding will be used between 
          R1 and R4.</t>

          <t>Note in this example that R3 and R4 cannot communicate directly with each other, because they dont 
          support a common forwarding technology </t>

        </section>

      </section>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document makes following requests of IANA.</t>

      <section title="New BGP SAFI">
        <t>New BGP SAFI code for "Classful Transport". Value 76.</t>

        <t>This will be used to create new AFI,SAFI pairs for IPv4, IPv6
        Classful Transport families. viz:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>"Inet, Classful Transport". AFI/SAFI = "1/76" for carrying IPv4
            Classful Transport prefixes.</t>

            <t>"Inet6, Classful Transport". AFI/SAFI = "2/76" for carrying
            IPv6 Classful Transport prefixes.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title="New Format for BGP Extended Community">
        <t>Please assign a new Format (Type high = 0xa) of extended community
        <xref target="RFC4360">EXT-COMM</xref> called "Transport Class" from
        the following registries:<list>
            <t>the "BGP Transitive Extended Community Types" registry, and</t>

            <t>the "BGP Non-Transitive Extended Community Types" registry.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Please assign the same low-order six bits for both allocations.</t>

        <t>This document uses this new Format with subtype 0x2 (route target),
        as a transitive extended community.</t>

        <t>The Route Target thus formed is called "Transport Class" route
        target extended community.</t>

        <t>Taking reference of <xref target="RFC7153">RFC7153</xref> ,
        following requests are made:</t>

        <section title="Existing registries to be modified">
          <section title="Registries for the &quot;Type&quot; Field">
            <section title="Transitive Types">
              <t>This registry contains values of the high-order octet (the
              "Type" field) of a Transitive Extended Community.<figure>
                  <artwork>Registry Name: BGP Transitive Extended Community
                  Types TYPE VALUE NAME + 0x0a Transitive Transport Class
                  Extended + Community (Sub-Types are defined in the +
                  "Transitive Transport Class Extended + Community Sub-Types"
                  registry) </artwork>
                </figure></t>
            </section>

            <section title="Non-Transitive Types">
              <t>This registry contains values of the high-order octet (the
              "Type" field) of a Non-transitive Extended Community.<figure>
                  <artwork> Registry Name: BGP Non-Transitive Extended
                  Community Types TYPE VALUE NAME + 0x4a Non-Transitive
                  Transport Class Extended + Community (Sub-Types are defined
                  in the + "Non-Transitive Transport Class Extended +
                  Community Sub-Types" registry)</artwork>
                </figure></t>
            </section>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section title="New registries to be created">
          <section title="Transitive &quot;Transport Class&quot; Extended Community Sub-Types Registry">
            <figure>
              <artwork> This registry contains values of the second octet (the
              "Sub-Type" field) of an extended community when the value of the
              first octet (the "Type" field) is 0x07. Registry Name:
              Transitive Transport Class Extended Community Sub-Types RANGE
              REGISTRATION PROCEDURE 0x00-0xBF First Come First Served
              0xC0-0xFF IETF Review SUB-TYPE VALUE NAME 0x02 Route Target
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>

          <section title="Non-Transitive &quot;Transport Class&quot; Extended Community Sub-Types Registry">
            <figure>
              <artwork> This registry contains values of the second octet (the
              "Sub-Type" field) of an extended community when the value of the
              first octet (the "Type" field) is 0x47. Registry Name:
              Non-Transitive Transport Class Extended Community Sub-Types
              RANGE REGISTRATION PROCEDURE 0x00-0xBF First Come First Served
              0xC0-0xFF IETF Review SUB-TYPE VALUE NAME 0x02 Route Target
              </artwork>
            </figure>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="MPLS OAM code points">
        <t>The following two code points are sought for Target FEC Stack
        sub-TLVs:</t>

        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>IPv4 BGP Classful Transport</t>

            <t>IPv6 BGP Classful Transport</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Mechanisms described in this document carry Transport routes in a new
      BGP address family. That minimizes possibility of these routes leaking
      outside the expected domain or mixing with service routes.</t>

      <t>When redistributing between SAFI 4 and SAFI 76 Classful Transport
      routes, there is a possibility of SAFI 4 routes mixing with SAFI 1
      service routes. To avoid such scenarios, it is RECOMMENDED that
      implementations support keeping SAFI 4 routes in a separate transport
      RIB, distinct from service RIB that contain SAFI 1 service routes.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8277.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4364.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4360.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4684.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4760.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7911.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8029.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7153.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8669.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4456.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8212.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8664.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9012.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8986.xml"?>

      <reference anchor="SRTE"
                 target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-idr-segment-routing-te-policy-08">
        <front>
          <title>Advertising Segment Routing Policies in BGP</title>

          <author fullname="Previdi" initials="S" role="editor"
                  surname="Previdi"/>

          <date day="18" month="11" year="2019"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RTC-Ext"
                 target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-zzhang-idr-bgp-rt-constrains-extension-00#section-2">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="RTC-Ext">Route Target Constrain Extension</title>

          <author fullname="Zhaohui" initials="Z" role="editor"
                  surname="Zhang"/>

          <date day="12" month="07" year="2020"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Intent-Routing"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-hr-spring-intentaware-routing-using-color-00#section-6.3.2">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="Intent-Routing">Intent-aware Routing using
          Color</title>

          <author fullname="Shraddha" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Hegde"/>

          <date day="14" month="07" year="2022"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="BGP-CT-UPDATE-PACKING-TEST"
                 target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/ietf-wg-idr/draft-ietf-idr-bgp-ct/main/update-packing-test-results.txt">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="BGP-CT-UPDATE-PACKING-TEST">BGP CT Update packing
          Test Results</title>

          <author fullname="Kaliraj" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Vairavakkalai"/>

          <date day="23" month="11" year="2022"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MPLS-NAMESPACES"
                 target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-kaliraj-bess-bgp-sig-private-mpls-labels-01#section-6.1">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MPLS namespaces">BGP signalled
          MPLS-namespaces</title>

          <author fullname="Kaliraj" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Vairavakkalai"/>

          <date day="11" month="06" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="BGP-LU-EPE"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-gredler-idr-bgplu-epe-14">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="BGP LU EPE">Egress Peer Engineering using
          BGP-LU</title>

          <author fullname="Hannes" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Gredler"/>

          <date day="06" month="07" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="PCEP-RSVP-COLOR"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-rajagopalan-pcep-rsvp-color-00">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="PCEP RSVP COLOR">Path Computation Element
          Protocol(PCEP) Extension for RSVP Color</title>

          <author fullname="Balaji" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Rajagopalan"/>

          <date day="15" month="01" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SRV6-INTER-DOMAIN"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-salih-spring-srv6-inter-domain-sids-00">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="SRV6-INTER-DOMAIN">SRv6 inter-domain mapping
          SIDs</title>

          <author fullname="Salih" initials="" role="editor" surname="K A"/>

          <date day="10" month="01" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SRV6-SERVICES"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-bess-srv6-services-07">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="SRV6-SERVICES">SRv6 BGP based Overlay
          Services</title>

          <author fullname="Gaurav Dawra" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Dawra"/>

          <date day="11" month="04" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="SRV6-MPLS-AGRWL"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-agrawal-spring-srv6-mpls-interworking/05/">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="SRV6-INTER-DOMAIN">SRv6 and MPLS interworking</title>

          <author fullname="Swadesh Agrawal" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Agrawal"/>

          <date day="22" month="02" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="FLOWSPEC-REDIR-IP"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-ietf-idr-flowspec-redirect-ip-02">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="FLOWSPEC-REDIR-IP">BGP Flow-Spec Redirect to IP
          Action</title>

          <author fullname="Adam Simpson" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Simpson"/>

          <date day="02" month="02" year="2015"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MULTI-NH-ATTR"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-kaliraj-idr-multinexthop-attribute-02#section-3.4.3">
        <front>
          <title abbrev="MULTI-NH-ATTR">BGP MultiNexthop Attribute</title>

          <author fullname="Kaliraj Vairavakkalai" initials="" role="editor"
                  surname="Vairavakkalai"/>

          <date day="28" month="12" year="2021"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="Appendix A" numbered="true"
             title="Applicability to Intra AS and different Inter AS deployments.">
      <t>As described in <xref target="RFC4364">BGP-VPN</xref> Section 10, in
      an option-C network, service routes (VPN-IPv4) are neither maintained
      nor distributed by the ASBRs. Transport routes are maintained in the
      ASBRs and propagated in BGP LU (SAFI 4) or BGP CT (SAFI 76).</t>

      <t>Section 18 illustrates how constructs of BGP CT work in an Inter AS
      option-C deployment. The BGP CT constructs: SAFI 76, Transport Class and
      Resolution Scheme are used in an option-C deploymnent.</t>

      <t>In Intra AS and Inter AS option-A, option-B scenarios, SAFI 76 may
      not be used, but the Transport Class and Resolution Scheme mechanisms
      are used to provide service mapping.</t>

      <t>This section illustrates how BGP CT constructs work in Intra AS and
      Inter AS option-A, B deployment scenarios.</t>

      <section title="Intra AS usecase">
        <section title="Topology">
          <figure>
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                                    [RR11]
                                     |
                                     +
              [CE21]---[PE11]-------[P1]------[PE12]------[CE31]
                     |                             |
                     +                             +
                     |                             |
               AS2               ...AS1...               AS3

             10.21.21.21 ---- Traffic Direction ----&gt; 10.31.31.31
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>This example shows a provider network Autonomous system AS1. It
          serves customers AS2, AS3. Traffic direction being described is CE21
          to CE31. CE31 may request a specific SLA (e.g. Gold for this
          traffic), when traversing this provider network.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Transport Layer">
          <t>AS1 uses RSVP-TE intra-domain tunnels between PE11 and PE12. And
          LDP tunnels for best effort traffic.</t>

          <t>The network has two Transport classes: Gold with transport class
          id 100, Bronze with transport class id 200. These transport classes
          are provisioned at the PEs. This creates the Resolution Schemes for
          these transport classes at these PEs.</t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Gold transport class.<list>
              <t>PE11_to_PE12_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE12_to_PE11_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Bronze transport class.<list>
              <t>PE11_to_PE12_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE11_to_PE12_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>These tunnels are provisioned to belong to transport class 100 or
          200.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Service Layer route exchange">
          <t>Service nodes PE11, PE12 negotiate service families (SAFI 128) on
          the BGP session with RR11. Service helper RR11 reflects service
          routes between the two PEs with nexthop unchanged. There are no
          tunnels for transport-class 100 or 200 from RR11 to the PEs.</t>

          <t>Forwarding happens using service routes at service nodes PE11,
          PE12. Routes received from CEs are not present in any other nodes'
          FIB in the provider network.</t>

          <t>CE31 advertises a route for example prefix 10.31.31.31 with
          nexthop self to PE12. CE31 can attach a Mapping Community
          Color:0:100 on this route, to indicate its request for Gold SLA. Or,
          PE11 can attach the same using locally configured policies.</t>

          <t>Consider CE31 is getting VPN service from PE12. The
          RD:10.31.31.31 route is readvertised in SAFI 128 by PE12 with
          nexthop self (10.12.12.12) and label V-L1, to RR11 with the Mapping
          Community Color:0:100 attached. This SAFI 128 route reaches PE11 via
          RR11 with the nexthop unchanged as PE12 and label V-L1. Now PE11 can
          resolve the PNH 10.12.12.12 using PE11_to_PE12_gold RSVP TE LSP.</t>

          <t>The IP FIB at PE11 VRF will have a route for 10.31.31.31 with a
          nexthop when resolved using Resolution Scheme belonging to the
          mapping community Color:0:100, points to a PE11_to_PE12_gold
          tunnel.</t>

          <t>BGP CT SAFI 76 is not used in this Intra AS deployment. But the
          Transport class and Resolution Scheme constructs are used to
          preserve end-to-end SLA.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Inter AS option-A usecase">
        <section title="Topology">
          <figure>
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                  [RR11]                        [RR21]
                    |                             |
                    +                             +
[CE31]---[PE11]----[P1]----[ASBR11]---[ASBR21]---[P2]---[PE21]----[CE41]
        |                           |                           |
        +                           +                           +
        |                           |                           |
  AS3               ..AS1..               ..AS2..                  AS4 

10.31.31.31          ---- Traffic Direction ----&gt;           10.41.41.41
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>This example shows two provider network Autonomous systems AS1,
          AS2. They serve L3VPN customers AS3, AS4 respectively. The ASBRs
          ASBR11 and ASBR21 have IP VRFs connected directly. The inter AS link
          is IP enabled with no MPLS forwarding.</t>

          <t>Traffic direction being described is CE31 to CE41. CE41 may
          request a specific SLA (e.g. Gold for this traffic), when traversing
          these provider core networks.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Transport Layer">
          <t>AS1 uses RSVP-TE intra-domain tunnels between PE11 and ASBR11.
          And LDP tunnels for best effort traffic. AS2 uses SRTE intra-domain
          tunnels between ASBR21 and PE21, and L-ISIS for best effort
          tunnels.</t>

          <t>The networks have two Transport classes: Gold with transport
          class id 100, Bronze with transport class id 200. These transport
          classes are provisioned at the PEs and ASBRs. This creates the
          Resolution Schemes for these transport classes at these PEs and
          ASBRs.</t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Gold transport class.<list>
              <t>PE11_to_ASBR11_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR11_to_PE11_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE21_to_ASBR21_gold - SRTE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR21_to_PE21_gold - SRTE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Bronze transport class.<list>
              <t>PE11_to_ASBR11_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR11_to_PE11_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE21_to_ASBR21_bronze - SRTE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR21_to_PE21_bronze - SRTE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>These tunnels are provisioned to belong to transport class 100 or
          200.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Service Layer route exchange">
          <t>Service nodes PE11, ASBR11 negotiate service familiy (SAFI 128)
          on the BGP session with RR11. Service helper RR11 reflects service
          routes between the PE11 and ASBR11 with nexthop unchanged. </t>

          <t> Similarly, in AS2 PE21, ASBR21 negotiate service family (SAFI
          128) on the BGP session with RR21, which reflects service routes
          between the PE21 and ASBR21 with nexthop unchanged .</t>

          <t>CE41 advertises a route for example prefix 10.41.41.41 with
          nexthop self to PE21 VRF. CE41 can attach a Mapping Community
          Color:0:100 on this route, to indicate its request for Gold SLA. Or,
          PE21 can attach the same using locally configured policies.</t>

          <t>Consider CE41 is getting VPN service from PE21. The
          RD:10.41.41.41 route is readvertised in SAFI 128 by PE21 with
          nexthop self (10.21.21.21) and label V-L1, to RR21 with the Mapping
          Community Color:0:100 attached. This SAFI 128 route reaches ASBR21
          via RR21 with the nexthop unchanged as PE21 and label V-L1. Now
          ASBR21 can resolve the PNH 10.21.21.21 using ASBR21_to_PE21_gold
          SRTE LSP.</t>

          <t>The IP FIB at ASBR21 VRF will have a route for 10.41.41.41 with a
          nexthop resolved using Resolution Scheme associated with mapping
          community Color:0:100, pointing to ASBR21_to_PE21_gold tunnel.</t>

          <t>This route is readvertised by ASBR21 on BGP session inside VRF
          with nexthop self. EBGP session peering on interface address. ASBR21
          acts like a CE to ASBR11, and the above mentioned process repeats in
          AS1, until route reaches PE11 and resolves over PE11_to_ASBR11_gold
          RSVP TE tunnel.</t>

          <t>Traffic traverses as IP packet on the following legs: CE31-PE11,
          ASBR11-ASBR21, PE21-CE41. And uses MPLS forwarding inside AS1, AS2
          core.</t>

          <t>BGP CT SAFI 76 is not used in this Inter AS option-A deployment.
          But the Transport class and Resolution Scheme constructs are used to
          preserve end-to-end SLA.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Inter AS option-B usecase">
        <section title="Topology">
          <figure>
            <artwork align="left" xml:space="preserve">
                  [RR13]                        [RR23]
                    |                             |
                    +                             +
[CE31]---[PE11]----[P1]----[ASBR12]---[ASBR21]---[P2]---[PE22]----[CE41]
        |                           |                           |
        +                           +                           +
        |                           |                           |
  AS3               ..AS1..               ..AS2..                  AS4 

10.31.31.31          ---- Traffic Direction ----&gt;           10.41.41.41
            </artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>This example shows two provider network Autonomous systems AS1,
          AS2. They serve L3VPN customers AS3, AS4 respectively. The ASBRs
          ASBR12 and ASBR21 dont have any IP VRFs . The inter AS link is MPLS
          forwarding enabled.</t>

          <t>Traffic direction being described is CE31 to CE41. CE41 may
          request a specific SLA (e.g. Gold for this traffic), when traversing
          these provider core networks.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Transport Layer">
          <t>AS1 uses RSVP-TE intra-domain tunnels between PE11 and ASBR21.
          And LDP tunnels for best effort traffic. AS2 uses SRTE intra-domain
          tunnels between ASBR21 and PE22, and L-ISIS for best effort
          tunnels.</t>

          <t>The networks have two Transport classes: Gold with transport
          class id 100, Bronze with transport class id 200. These transport
          classes are provisioned at the PEs and ASBRs. This creates the
          Resolution Schemes for these transport classes at these PEs and
          ASBRs.</t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Gold transport class.<list>
              <t>PE11_to_ASBR12_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR12_to_PE11_gold - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE22_to_ASBR21_gold - SRTE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR21_to_PE22_gold - SRTE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>Following tunnels exist for Bronze transport class.<list>
              <t>PE11_to_ASBR12_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR12_to_PE11_bronze - RSVP-TE tunnel</t>

              <t>PE22_to_ASBR21_bronze - SRTE tunnel</t>

              <t>ASBR21_to_PE22_bronze - SRTE tunnel</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>These tunnels are provisioned to belong to transport class 100 or
          200.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Service Layer route exchange">
          <t>Service nodes PE11, ASBR12 negotiate service familiy (SAFI 128)
          on the BGP session with RR13. Service helper RR13 reflects service
          routes between the PE11 and ASBR12 with nexthop unchanged. </t>

          <t> Similarly, in AS2 PE22, ASBR21 negotiate service family (SAFI
          128) on the BGP session with RR23, which reflects service routes
          between the PE22 and ASBR21 with nexthop unchanged .</t>

          <t>ASBR21 and ASBR12 negotiate SAFI 128 between them, and
          readvertise L3VPN routes with nexthop self, allocating new labels.
          EBGP session peering on interface address. </t>

          <t>CE41 advertises a route for example prefix 10.41.41.41 with
          nexthop self to PE22 VRF. CE41 can attach a Mapping Community
          Color:0:100 on this route, to indicate its request for Gold SLA. Or,
          PE22 can attach the same using locally configured policies.</t>

          <t>Consider CE41 is getting VPN service from PE22. The
          RD:10.41.41.41 route is readvertised in SAFI 128 by PE22 with
          nexthop self (10.22.22.22) and label V-L1, to RR23 with the Mapping
          Community Color:0:100 attached. This SAFI 128 route reaches ASBR21
          via RR23 with the nexthop unchanged as PE22 and label V-L1. Now
          ASBR21 can resolve the PNH 10.22.22.22 using ASBR21_to_PE22_gold
          SRTE LSP.</t>

          <t>Next, ASBR21 readvertises the RD:10.41.41.41 route with nexthop
          self to ASBR12, with a newly allocated MPLS label, V-L2. Forwarding
          for this label is installed to Swap V-L1, and Push labels for
          ASBR21_to_PE22_gold tunnel. </t>

          <t>ASBR12 further readvertises the RD:10.41.41.41 route via RR13 to
          PE11 with nexthop self 10.12.12.12. PE1 resolves the nexthop
          10.12.12.12 over PE11_to_ASBR11_gold RSVP TE tunnel.</t>

          <t>Traffic traverses as IP packet on the following legs: CE31-PE11,
          PE21-CE41. And uses MPLS forwarding on ASBR11-ASBR21 link, and
          inside AS1, AS2 core.</t>

          <t>BGP CT SAFI 76 is not used in this Inter AS option-B deployment.
          But the Transport class and Resolution Scheme constructs are used to
          preserve end-to-end SLA.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Appendix B" numbered="true"
             title="Why reuse RFC 8277 and RFC 4364?">
      <t>RFC 4364 is one of the key design patterns produced by networking
      industry. It introduced virtualization and allowed sharing of resources
      in service provider space with multiple tenant networks, providing
      isolated and secure Layer3 VPN services. This design pattern has been
      reused since to provide other service layer virtualizations like Layer2
      virtualization (VPLS, L2VPN, EVPN), ISO virtualization, ATM
      virtualization, Flowspec VPN.</t>

      <t> It is to be noted that these services have different NLRI encoding.
      L3VPN Service family that binds MPLS label to an IP prefix use RFC 8277
      encoding, and others define different NLRI encodings.</t>

      <t>BGP CT reuses RFC 4364 procedures to slice a transport network into
      multiple transport planes that different service routes can bind to,
      using Color. </t>

      <t> BGP CT reuses RFC 8277 because it precisely fits the purpose. viz.
      In a MPLS network, BGP CT needs to bind MPLS label for transport
      endpoints which are IPv4 or IPv6 endpoints, and disambiguate between
      multiple instances of those endpoints in multiple transport planes.
      Hence use of RD:IP_Prefix and carrying a Label for it as specified in
      RFC 8277 works well for this purpose. </t>

      <t>Another advantage of using the precise encoding as defined in RFC
      4364 and RFC 8277 is that it allows to interoperate with BGP speakers
      that support SAFI 128. This can be useful during transition, until all
      BGP speakers in the network support BGP CT.</t>

      <t>In future, if RFC 8277 evolves into a typed NLRI, that does not carry
      Label in the NLRI, BGP CT will be compatible with that as-well. In
      essence, BGP CT encoding is compatible with existing deployed
      technologies (RFC 4364, RFC 8277) and will adapt to any changes RFC 8277
      mechanisms undergo in future. </t>

      <t>This is a more pragmatic approach which leverages the benefits of
      time tested design patterns proposed in RFC 4364 and RFC 8277. Moreover,
      this approach greatly reduces operational training costs and protocol
      compatibility considerations as it complements and works well with
      existing protocol machineries. This problem does not need reinventing
      the wheel with brand new NLRI and procedures.</t>

      <t>This is a more pragmatic approach, rather than abandoning time tested
      design pattern like RFC 4364 and RFC 8277, just to invent something
      completely new that is not backward compatible with existing
      deployements.</t>

      <section numbered="true" title="Update packing considerations">
        <t>BGP CT carries transport class as an attribute. This means routes
        that dont share the same transport class cannot be packed into same
        Update message. Update packing in BGP CT will be similar to RFC 8277
        family routes carrying attributes like communities or extended
        communities. Service families like SAFI 128 have considerably more
        scale than transport families like SAFI 4 or SAFI 76, which carry only
        loopbacks. Update packing mechanisms that scale for SAFI 128 routes
        will scale similarly for SAFI 76 routes also.</t>

        <t>The document <xref target="Intent-Routing">Intent-aware Routing
        using Color </xref> section 6.3.2 documents suggests scaling numbers
        for transport network where BGP CT can be deployed. Experiments were
        conducted with this scale to find the convergence time with BGP CT for
        those scaling numbers. Scenarios involving BGP CT carrying IPv4
        endpoints, IPv6 endpoints and IPv6 endpoints with SRv6 SID were
        tested.</t>

        <t>Tests were conducted with 1.9 million BGP CT route scale (387K
        endpoints in 5 transport classes). Initial convergence time for all
        cases was less than 2 minutes, This experiment proves that carrying
        transport class information as an attribute keeps BGP convergence
        within acceptable range. Details of the experiment and test results
        are available in <xref target="BGP-CT-UPDATE-PACKING-TEST">BGP CT
        Update packing Test Results </xref>.</t>

        <t>Further, even in today's BGP LU deployments each egress node
        originates BGP LU route for it's loopback, with some attributes like
        community identifying the originating node or region, and AIGP TLV.
        These attributes may be unique per egress node, thus do not help with
        update packing in transport layer family routes.</t>
      </section>

      <section numbered="true" title="Scaling using MPLS Namespaces">
        <t> kaliraj text </t>

        <section numbered="true" title="Illustration.">
          <t> text </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Appendix C" numbered="true"
             title="Compatibility with SR-PCE architecture">
      <t> natv text </t>

      <t>Describe how BGP CT Mapping community is a generalization of Color
      Extended Community as used in SR-PCE architecture.</t>

      <section numbered="true" title="Illustration.">
        <t> text </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Contributors" numbered="false" title="Contributors">
      <section anchor="Co-Authors" numbered="false" title="Co-Authors">
        <author fullname="Israel Means" initials="I" surname="Means">
          <organization abbrev="">AT&amp;T</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>2212 Avenida Mara,</street>

              <city>Chula Vista</city>

              <region>California</region>

              <code>91914</code>

              <country>USA</country>
            </postal>

            <email>israel.means@att.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Csaba Mate" initials="CS" surname="Mate">
          <organization abbrev="">KIFU, Hungarian NREN</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>35 Vaci street,</street>

              <city>Budapest</city>

              <region/>

              <code>1134</code>

              <country>Hungary</country>
            </postal>

            <email>ietf@nop.hu</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Deepak J Gowda" initials="J" surname="Gowda">
          <organization abbrev="">Extreme Networks</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>55 Commerce Valley Drive West, Suite 300,</street>

              <city>Thornhill, Toronto,</city>

              <region>Ontario</region>

              <code>L3T 7V9</code>

              <country>Canada</country>
            </postal>

            <email>dgowda@extremenetworks.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Other Contributors" numbered="false"
               title="Other Contributors">
        <author fullname="Balaji Rajagopalan" initials="B."
                surname="Rajagopalan">
          <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>Electra, Exora Business Park~Marathahalli - Sarjapur
              Outer Ring Road,</street>

              <city>Bangalore</city>

              <region>KA</region>

              <code>560103</code>

              <country>India</country>
            </postal>

            <email>balajir@juniper.net</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Reshma Das" initials="D." surname="Das">
          <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>1133 Innovation Way,</street>

              <city>Sunnyvale</city>

              <region>CA</region>

              <code>94089</code>

              <country>US</country>
            </postal>

            <email>dreshma@juniper.net</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Rajesh M" initials="M">
          <organization>Juniper Networks, Inc.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>Electra, Exora Business Park~Marathahalli - Sarjapur
              Outer Ring Road,</street>

              <city>Bangalore</city>

              <region>KA</region>

              <code>560103</code>

              <country>India</country>
            </postal>

            <email>mrajesh@juniper.net</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Chaitanya Yadlapalli" initials="C"
                surname="Yadlapalli">
          <organization abbrev="">AT&amp;T</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>200 S Laurel Ave,</street>

              <city>Middletown,</city>

              <region>NJ</region>

              <code>07748</code>

              <country>USA</country>
            </postal>

            <email>cy098d@att.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Gyan Mishra" initials="G." surname="Mishra">
          <organization>Verizon Inc.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>13101 Columbia Pike</street>

              <city>Silver Spring</city>

              <region>MD</region>

              <code>20904</code>

              <country>USA</country>
            </postal>

            <email>gyan.s.mishra@verizon.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Mazen Khaddam" initials="M" surname="Khaddam">
          <organization abbrev="">Cox Communications Inc.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street/>

              <city>Atlanta</city>

              <region>GA</region>

              <code/>

              <country>USA</country>
            </postal>

            <email>mazen.khaddam@cox.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Rafal Jan Szarecki" initials="R" surname="Szarecki">
          <organization abbrev="">Google.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>1160 N Mathilda Ave, Bldg 5,</street>

              <city>Sunnyvale,</city>

              <region>CA</region>

              <code>94089</code>

              <country>USA</country>
            </postal>

            <email>szarecki@google.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Xiaohu Xu" initials="X" surname="Xu">
          <organization abbrev="">Capitalonline.</organization>

          <address>
            <postal>
              <street/>

              <city>Beijing</city>

              <region/>

              <code/>

              <country>China</country>
            </postal>

            <email>xiaohu.xu@capitalonline.net</email>
          </address>
        </author>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false"
             title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The authors thank Jeff Haas, John Scudder, Susan Hares, Moses
      Nagarajah, Navaneetha Krishnan, Ravi M R, Chandrasekar Ramachandran,
      Shradha Hegde, Richard Roberts, Krzysztof Szarkowicz, John E Drake,
      Srihari Sangli, Vijay Kestur, Santosh Kolenchery, Robert Raszuk, Ahmed
      Darwish, Aravind Srinivas Srinivasa Prabhakar, Moshiko Nayman, Chris
      Trip for the valuable discussions and review comments.</t>

      <t>The decision to not reuse SAFI 128 and create a new address-family to
      carry these transport-routes was based on suggestion made by Richard
      Roberts and Krzysztof Szarkowicz.</t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
